Register of the French subject collection, 1665-2011
Hoover Institution Archives
French subject collection,
1665-2011
XX746
Hoover Institution Archives
104 manuscript boxes, 17 microfilm reels, 8 phonotape reels, 9 phonotape cassettes, 13 videotape cassettes (48.4 linear feet)
Pamphlets, leaflets, clippings, serial issues, election campaign literature, and other printed matter, relating to political, social and economic conditions in France, especially during the Fifth Republic; elections; socialist and communist movements; radicalism, especially student radicalism, during the events of 1968; freemasonry; and miscellaneous aspects of pre-twentieth-century French history.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Content of Collection
Pamphlets, leaflets, clippings, serial issues, election campaign literature, and other printed matter, relating to political, social and economic conditions in France, especially during the Fifth Republic; elections; socialist and communist movements; radicalism, especially student radicalism, during the events of 1968; freemasonry; and miscellaneous aspects of pre-twentieth-century French history.
Freemasons--France.; Communism--France.; Elections--France.; France--History.; France--Politics and government--20th century.; General Strike, France, 1968.; Phonotapes.; Radicalism--France.; Socialism--France.; Student movements--France.; Video tapes.
- Subject File, 1665-1994 (Box 1-99)
  Scope and Contents note
  Pamphlets, leaflets, clippings, serial issues, campaign literature, and other printed matter, relating to political conditions and elections in France, especially during the Fifth Republic; socialist and communist movements in France; French radicalism, especially student radicalism during the events of 1968; freemasonry in France; and miscellaneous aspects of pre-twentieth-century French history.
  - General (Box 1)
    - Miscellany
      - 1665-1871
        - Correspondence, decrees, maps, drawings, and printed matter, relating to miscellaneous aspects of French governmental administration under the Bourbon and Orleanist monarchies and to the Paris Commune of 1871. Includes original decrees issued by Louis XIV, Louis XV, and Louis Philippe. In French, 1665-1871
      - 1912-1947
        - Bulletins, newspaper issues, and printed matter, relating to various social and cultural conditions in France. Includes copies of the statutes of the Federation Nationale des Syndicats Maritimes, and of the annual report of the Chambre Consultative des Associations Ouvrieres de Production, Mainly in French, 1912, 1925.
    - Freemasons. Clippings, serial issues, pamphlets, bulletins, and election campaign material, relating to Freemasonry in France, Freemasons in politics, French politics and international relations in the 1920s and 1930s, the Popular Front, rightist movements in France, and occupied France during World War II. In French, 1807-1947 (Box 2-21)
    - Socialism. Clippings, newspaper and periodical issues, bulletins, pamphlets and leaflets, issued by communist, socialist, syndicalist and trade-union organizations in France, relating to the international and French communist, socialist, syndicalist and trade-union movements. Includes resolutions of the third national congress of Syndicats et Groupes Corporatifs Ouvriers de France, In French, 1888-1947, 1888. (Box 22-30)
    - Communism. Articles from leftist French newspapers, relating to the movement for a Third International and to the mutiny of French sailors in the Black Sea. Translations of articles from French and Russian newspapers, relating to the development of a French communist party and to its adherence to the Third International, 1917-1919, 1919-1920 (Box 30, 103)
  - 1870-1940
    - Post World War I reparations. Table, 1924, indicating French war reparation expenditures and internal and foreign debt for and budget for 1924, 1923 (Box 30)
    - Souvarine, Boris. Photocopies of Jeannine Verdes-Leroux's articles on Boris Souvarine and reviews of her book A ContreCourant, Ecrits 1925-1939, 1983-1985 (Box 89)
    - Miscellany (Box 97)
      - Flyer scattered over Paris by airplane, urging Frenchmen to subscribe to defense bonds. In French, October 1938
      - Sheet music of song written for French reservists, In French, 1939.
  - 1945-1958
    - Communist Party
      - Speech delivered by Secretary Jacques Duclos at the Marigny Theater, Paris, on English translation, March 20, 1946.
      - Anti-American flyer, In French, 1951.
    - Elections - Flyers, leaflets, postcards, ballots, and stamps put out by "Paix et Liberte" and the "Parti republicain radical et radical-socialiste" for the 1956 general elections (Box 94)
  - 1958-
    - General. Miscellaneous election leaflets, pamphlets, newspapers, magazines, and government documents, relating to political conditions in France. In French, 1958-1981 (Box 31-83, 98)
    - Bi-Centennial celebration of the Revolution of 1789. Correspondence, articles, flyers, circulars, newsletters, and stickers, issued by the Association 15 Août 1989 and relating to the demonstration held in Paris on August 15, 1989, protesting the celebration of the French Revolution. In French (Box 96)
    - Economy. Booklet by Morvan Duhamel, relating to the French industry since 1955. In French, 1987 (Box 97)
    - Education (Box 89)
      - Leaflets and stickers denouncing the government's education policies, gathered at a demonstration which took place at Versailles on March 4, 1984
      - Newsletters and flyers, issued by various education syndicates, 1989-1991 (Box 97)
    - Elections
      - Material relating to the general elections of June in Toulouse, 1968. (Box 89)
      - Miscellany relating to the Presidential election of May 5, 1974. (Box 97)
      - Material relating to the local elections of March, 1985. (Box 89)
      - Material relating to the legislative and regional elections of March 16, 1986. (Box 90-94)
      - Material relating to the Presidential elections of April 24 and May 8, and to the legislative elections of June 5 and 12, 1988. (Box 95-96)
      - Material relating to the local and regional elections of March 22, 1992. (Box 98-99)
    - Immigration
      - General. Study on the immigration question in France, and racist and xenophobic newsletters, magazines, and flyers, In French, n.d., 1990. (Box 96)
      - Nationality code. Pamphlet, In French, 1987. (Box 97)
    - Miscellany. Brochures, relating to economic development in the island of La Reunion. In French, 1983-1990
    - Political parties
      - General. Broadsides, leaflets, and election campaign material, consisting of electoral and other propaganda from various political parties. In French, 1950-1961
        - 1950-1961 (Box 89)
        - 1993 (Box 98)
      - Communist Party (Box 97, 98)
        - General. Brochures and leaflets, 1990.
        - Excerpt from the resolution of the 27th Congress of the Communist Party, published in l'Humanite of, December 26, 1990
      - Generation Ecologie. Miscellany, 1990-1991 (Box 99)
      - Front National. Five posters issued as part of the Front National's two-phase propaganda campaign launched in February 1991, with the message "Le Pen, fast" written in French, Hebrew, Arabic, Chinese, and Russian. (Box 97)
      - Mouvement des Democrates. Miscellany, 1993 (Box 99)
      - Socialist Party
        - General. Printed matter, 1993
        - Stickers, 1968 (Box 89)
        - Newsletter and ephemera, In French, 1990. (Box 96)
      - Union Pour la Democratie Francaise. Miscellany, 1993 (Box 99)
    - Public opinion - Gulf War of 1991. Correspondence, newsletters, and flyers, relating to the Gulf War of 1991 and mostly calling for demonstrations against it (Box 97)
    - Student Revolt, 1968 (Box 84-88, 98)
      - General. Pamphlets, leaflets, and serial issues relating to the student-worker revolt of May 1968. In French
      - Miscellany relating to the student-worker revolt of May 1968. In French (Box 89)
      - Photocopies of political tracts, flyers, and broadsides relating to the student-worker revolt at the University of Toulouse in May-June 1968. In French
      - Postcards reproducing posters and slogans of the student-worker revolt gathered in booklet form, 1988 (Box 97)
      - Circulars and newsletters issued by various student organizations during the student-worker revolt of 1968
- Audi-Visual Material, 1958-1988.
  Video and phonotapes, microfilms and cassettes relating to the French Fifth Republic, the Student Revolt of 1968 and the elections of 1988. See also the Hoover Institution Library for 54 microfilm reels of daily French newspapers for the period May 2-July 3, 1968, and 3 microfilm reels of weekly French newspapers for the period April 20-July 4, 1968, covering the student uprising and the June parliamentary elections.
  - 8 phonotapes of interviews of personalities involved in the events of May 1968; 2 videotapes relating to the legislative elections of June 5 and 12, 1988 (Tape-cabinet Tape cabinet)
  - 8 phonotape cassettes of interviews of various political personalities, conducted by Radio France, 1970-1978 (Cassette-cabinet Cassette cabinet)
    - Radio France interview of Edgar Fauve, 06 May 1970 (Cassette-cabinet Cassette cabinet)
      Access
      Use copy reference number: xx746_a_0009667
    - Radio France interview of Jacques Chirac, 12 December 1977 (Cassette-cabinet Cassette cabinet)
      Use copy reference number: xx746_a_0009660
    - Radio France interview of Jacques Duclos, 03 April 1970 (Cassette-cabinet Cassette cabinet)
      Use copy reference number: xx746_a_0009664
    - Radio France interview of Jean Lecanuet, 26 December 1977 (Cassette-cabinet Cassette cabinet)
      Use copy reference number: xx746_a_0009676
    - Radio France interview of Michel Rocard, 16 February 1978 (Cassette-cabinet Cassette cabinet)
      Use copy reference number: xx746_a_0009670
    - Radio France interview of Pierre Mendès France, 02 February 1973 (Cassette-cabinet Cassette cabinet)
      Use copy reference number: xx746_a_0009682
    - Radio France interview of Rene Levesque, 04 February 1977 (Cassette-cabinet Cassette cabinet)
      Use copy reference number: xx746_a_0009679
    - Radio France interview of Simone Veil, 06 May 1975 (Cassette-cabinet Cassette cabinet)
      Use copy reference number: xx746_a_0009673
  - 1 phonotape cassette relating to the legislative elections of June 5 and 12, 1988
    Use copy reference number: xx746_a_0009659
  - 17 microfilm reels of newspaper issues from the French and Algerian press analyzing the legislative elections of 1958 (Microfilm-cabinet Microfilm cabinet)
- Incremental Materials 2000-2007, 1918-2007 (Folder 101-102)
  - Newsletters, 1997-2000 (Folder 101)
  - Newsletters, 2000 (Folder 101)
  - Election campaign literature, 2001-2002 (Folder 101)
  - Printed matter and memorabilia (4 folders), 1918 and n.d. (Folder 102)
  - Election campaign literature (17 folders), 2005-2007 (Folder 102)
  - Election campaign literature, 2007 (Folder 102)
- Incremental Materials (Box 103-104)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described. Contact us at hooverarchivesinfo@stanford.edu